Finding Aid for Fred E. Schwab papers, 1930-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Fred E. Schwab papers
1930-2009
Schwab, Fred E., 1918-2009.
2011022 Aa 2; Ac
Fred E. Schwab was an influential member of the plastics community in the Detroit area. A German immigrant, he opened and ran several plastic manufacturing businesses, including Schwab & Frank and Schwab Plastics, which focused on styrofoam products and later automotive parts. He was also a founding member of the Society of Plastics Engineers. The collection includes personal materials, photographs, and professional files relating to his association with various plastics firms.
2 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Marianne Schwab (donor no. 10463 ) in November 2010.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Fred E. Schwab emigrated from Germany immediately prior to World War II and founded a series of successful plastics manufacturing businesses in southeast Michigan before retiring in 2002.
Fred Schwab was born in 1918 in Frankfurt, Germany. His father was a lawyer, judge, and businessman who sold rubber products across Germany. While in Frankfurt, Schwab worked at his father's rubber manufacturing business and at a dental laboratory where he learned to work with acrylic polymers. In 1937, his family insisted he leave Germany to live with an uncle in New York. Schwab's parents and brother later managed to escape Germany for England, though both his father and brother spent time in Buchenwald.
After moving to New York, Schwab managed to secure a loan from his uncle, to start a plastics business with Jack Frank in Detroit. Schwab & Frank initially made its name selling acrylic materials to dental supply manufacturers. Schwab & Frank later expanded the business to produce other kinds of plastics. They pioneered multi-color extrusion, polystyrene molding and cutting techniques, and processes for extruded coiling. They used these techniques to produce novelty items including jewelry, Christmas decor, and telephone cords. After being granted American citizenship, Schwab took a leave of absence from Schwab & Frank and joined the United States Army as a translator in 1943. During that time, he also married his wife, Marianne.
Following his return to Schwab and Frank, Schwab developed an increasing interest in the automotive industry. In 1952, he bought out his partner and founded Schwab Plastics, which focused on the production of automotive and industrial parts.
After facing substantial financial difficulties, Schwab Plastics was sold to the Lus-Trus Corporation in 1958, where Schwab served as the sales manager. After leaving Lus-Trus, Schwab helped found Group Four Sales to assist plastics manufacturers with both sales and technical matters.
Schwab was also influential in the founding of the Society of Plastics Engineers in 1942. In 1987, he was inducted into the Plastics Hall of Fame. He received an Honorary Doctorate of Humane Letters in 1996 from Ferris State University in Michigan.
The Fred E. Schwab collection has been divided into three series: PERSONAL LIFE, PLASTICS, and PHOTOGRAPHS. The collection documents Schwab's professional endeavors in the plastic community in addition to elements from his personal life.
Subjects:
Emmerich, Hugo.; Schwab, Fred E.; Schwab & Frank.; Schwab Plastics.; Manufacturers--Michigan.; Plastics industry and trade--Michigan.; Property claims--Germany.; Germany--Emigration and immigration.; United States--Emigration and immigration.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Schwab, Fred E.; Schwab & Frank.; Schwab Plastics.
Genre Terms:
Advertisements.; Photographs.
- Personal Life
  PERSONAL LIFE (.5 liner feet, 1930-2009) includes correspondence, official documents, and press clippings. The majority of the correspondence relates to claims against the German government relating to property confiscated from the Schwab family during World War II. It also includes a number of press clippings related to Fred Schwab and a series of autobiographical timelines written by Mr. Schwab over a number of years. A significant portion of this series is in German.
  - Army Career, 1945-1946 (Box 1)
  - Awards and recognitions, 1969-1991 (Box 1)
    (see also oversized folder)
  - Biographies, 1962-1988 (Box 1)
  - Business Cards, circa 1950-1980 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Emigration, 1939-1947 (Box 1)
    - Emmerich, Hugo
      - Gebrueder Feisenberger property claims, 1938-1950; 2 folders (Box 1)
      - General German property claims, 1939-1954; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Feisenberger family, 1930-1949 (Box 1)
    - Job search, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1937-1992 (Box 1)
    - Schwab, Marianne, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Emigration
    - Letters of Introduction, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Official documents, 1935-1962 (Box 1)
  - Press clippings, 1946-2009 (Box 1)
  - Sales trip, Germany, 1971 (Box 1)
- Plastics
  PLASTICS (1.5 linear feet, 1931-1998) documents Fred Schwab's career in plastics and his involvement in the larger plastics community. It is organized chronologically by Schwab's various business endeavors and is divided into the following sub-series: loose scrapbook materials, Schwab & Frank, Frank Paper Products, Schwab Plastics, Lus-Trus, Group Four Sales, the Society of Plastics Engineers, and miscellaneous materials.
  - Loose Scrapbook Material
    The loose scrapbook materials include advertisements, blue prints, and correspondence as organized by Fred Schwab.
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - 1937-1945 (Box 1)
    - 1946 (Box 1)
    - 1947 (Box 1)
    - (clippings), 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - 1948 (Box 1)
    - 1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 1)
    - 1952 (Box 1)
    - 1953 (Box 1)
  - Schwab & Frank
    Schwab & Frank files include a substantial series of correspondence relating to patent, trademark, and licensing issues. It also includes files relating to the Board of Directors and advertisements for Schwab and Frank products.
    - Advertisements, circa 1950 (Box 1)
    - Board of Directors record book, 1931-1955 (Box 1)
      (includes Articles of Incorporation, bylaws and meeting minutes)
    - Building Plan, undated (Box 1)
    - Charts and formulas, 1953-1955 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - Emmerich, Hugo, 1952-1955 (Box 1)
      - Frank, Jack, 1943-1944 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 1938-1953 (Box 1)
      - Reaume & Silloway, 1943 (Box 1)
      - Stern, Herbert, 1943 (Box 1)
      - Woodhams, Robert
        - Licensing, 1947-1954 (Box 1)
        - Patents
          - Coiling, 1946-1957 (Box 1)
          - Extrusion, 1946-1950 (Box 1)
          - Miscellaneous, 1946-1953 (Box 1)
        - Trademarks, 1946-1954 (Box 1)
    - Definitions, circa 1950 (Box 1)
    - Diagrams, 1940-1953 (Box 1)
    - Employee Contract, circa 1945 (Box 1)
    - Lease, 1947 (Box 2)
    - License Agreements, 1947-1954 (Box 2)
    - Molders' Management Meeting, 1953 (Box 2)
    - Partnership
      - Agreement, 1937-1947 (Box 2)
      - Reorganization, circa 1954 (Box 2)
    - Press Clippings, 1942-1954 (Box 2)
    - Price Lists, 1941-1954 (Box 2)
    - Shareholder Meetings, 1954-1955 (Box 2)
    - Trademarks, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Frank Paper Products
    The Frank Paper Products files include information and advertisements for products marketed under the Frank Paper Products name.
    - Advertisements, circa 1954 (Box 2)
    - Building sale, 1954 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 2)
    - Price Lists, 1950-1954 (Box 2)
  - Schwab Plastics Corporation
    The Schwab Plastics files include correspondence relating to patents, trademarks, and licensing agreements in addition to correspondence relating to the financial failure of the corporation and its subsequent sale to Lus-Trus. The Schwab Plastics files also include information and advertisements for Schwab Plastics products.
    - Advertisements and Price Lists, circa 1958 (Box 2)
    - Board of Directors
      - Board of Directors and Shareholders meetings, 1956; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Schwab Plastics record book, 1969 (Box 2)
        (includes Articles of Incorporation, bylaws, and stock certificates)
    - Building Plans, circa 1964 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - Bankruptcy, 1958 (Box 2)
      - Merger, 1956-1959 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1955-1969 (Box 2)
      - Woodhams, Robert
        - Licensing, 1956-1964 (Box 2)
        - Patents, 1962-1965; 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Trademarks, 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Emmerich Shareholder Agreement, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Facilities Reports, circa 1960 (Box 2)
    - Merger, 1958; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Products
      - Diagrams, 1957-1965 (Box 2)
      - Lists, 1959 (Box 2)
    - Shareholder Meetings (Box 2)
    - UAW Contract, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Lus-Trus
    Lus-Trus includes correspondence and notes from Board of Directors meetings.
    - Advertising, circa 1960 (Box 2)
    - Board of Directors meetings, 1959-1960; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Group Four Sales
    Files from Group Four Sales include limited administrative information and records related to sales commissions made by Schwab.
    - Administration, circa 1970 (Box 2)
    - Commissions, 1970-1988 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1991 (Box 2)
    - Patents, 1975-1987 (Box 2)
  - Society of Plastics Engineers
    Society of Plastics Engineers includes miscellaneous files and correspondence in addition to records on the Society's 50th Anniversary celebration.
    - 50th Anniversary, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1948-1998 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    The miscellaneous files include work completed independently by Fred Schwab and undated production blue prints and diagrams.
    - Auto Industry, collected materials, 1977-1999 (Box 2)
    - Macoid, 1963-1970 (Box 2)
    - Plans and Diagrams, undated (Box 2)
- Photographs
  PHOTOGRAPHS (1945-1996) contains personal photographs of Fred Schwab in addition to photographs of Schwab's plastic factories and various plastics products produced by Schwab.
  - Advertising mock-ups, circa 1950 (Box 2)
  - Ferris State, 1996-1997 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous factory, circa 1945-1950 (Box 2)
  - Personal, 1945-1995 (Box 2)
  - Production Items, circa 1950 (Box 2)
  - Schwab & Frank factory, circa 1945 (Box 2)
  - Schwab Plastics factory, circa 1955 (Box 2)
  - Society of Plastics Engineers, circa 1945-1996 (Box 2)